Guide to the Sholem Asch Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sholem Asch papers
1923-1949
1926-1949
GEN MSS 115
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
18.2
(23 boxes)
The papers contain most of Asch's major works as a novelist, including the controversial Der Man fun Notseres. The Writings series which is made up of Novels, Plays, Essays and Appeals and Other Writings, are written mostly in Yiddish, and includes reviews, playbills, programs, photographs of productions of plays. The correspondence is a selection of letters to Asch from many prominent Jewish writers and organizations. There is a series of letters from Stefan Zweig, as well as a large amount of correspondence with PEN clubs throughout Europe. Asch's concern for the Jews in Europe before and after the second World War is a constant subject in his writings and correspondence. There are also photographs of Asch and his family and friends, clippings of articles about Asch, postcards, and a bust of Asch by Morice Lipsi.
Asch, Sholem, 1880-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection is comprised of gifts from Sholem Asch in 1939, and from Louis M. Rabinowitz in 1944, the latter as part of the larger gift of the Asch-Rabinowitz Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
SHOLEM ASCH (1880-1957)
Sholem Asch, Yiddish novelist, dramatist, essayist, activist and short story writer, was born in Poland in 1880 and emigrated to the United States in 1910. Asch is known both for popularizing Yiddish literature internationally and for the controversy that resulted from the publication of his trilogy, Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene, 1939), Der Sheliekh (The Apostle, 1943), and Meri (Mary, 1949). In these works Asch explored the origins of Christianity from a Jewish perspective. Accusations from within the American Jewish community that he was preaching conversion to Christianity prompted a self-imposed exile in 1954 from the United States to Israel. Asch died in London three years later.
Bernhard Knollenberg, the Librarian of Yale University, asked Asch to donate the manuscript of Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene) to the Yale University Library in 1939. Asch complied, explaining in the introduction to the Catalogue of Hebrew and Yiddish Manuscripts and Books from the Library of Sholem Asch (New Haven: Yale University Library, 1945) that the gift of this manuscript to Yale precluded the placement of his manuscripts and books at any other library: "I knew full well that the rest of my manuscripts must come there, too, to the same place where the main product of my life-work is reposing. And where my own manuscripts have found a home, there too must dwell my books." Asch continues, explaining why he chose to grant Knollenberg's request:
I have sought a home for my collection not in a Jewish
institution, but in a general American one. I believe it is
the duty of American Jewry to rebuild the institutions of
Jewish learning in the new hospitable home which they have
found.... Jews must also see to it that the spirit of
Judaism, Jewish learning, should be properly and worthily
represented in the general temples of knowledge in the land.
In 1944, through the generosity of Louis M. Rabinowitz, the University Library acquired Asch's collection of manuscripts and books, designating it the Asch-Rabinowitz Collection. This immensely rich library documenting European Jewish life and culture from the 15th through the early 20th century, is well described in the catalogue quoted above, compiled by Dr. Leon Nemoy, Curator of Judaica at Yale. Asch himself provided the summation of the scholarly importance of the his own papers included in the Asch-Rabinowitz Collection, in the catalogue's introduction: "The leaves of my manuscripts represent the days of my life, for I had no other life outside of my works."
Scope and Contents
The Sholem Asch Papers consist of writings, correspondence, printed material, photographs, and artwork which document the life and work of the Yiddish writer and activist Sholem Asch. The collection spans the years 1907 to 1956, the bulk of the material from 1923 to 1949, during which time Asch wrote all of his major novels.
The Papers are housed in 23 boxes (18.20 linear feet) and are arranged into four series: Writings, Correspondence, Photographs, and Other Papers. Boxes 17-23 contain Oversize items. The collection was previously classified as Hebrew Manuscripts +45 and Asch Collection ZA1-ZA6 and Folio 217-218. These old call numbers are either on the items themselves, or have been noted on folders as an aid to researchers who may wish to locate materials previously cited under that numbering system. Transliteration and verification of titles which appear in this listing was provided by Keith Weiser, a student assistant.
The Sholem Asch Papers contain most of Asch's major works as a novelist, including the extremely controversial Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene), although it does not contain such earlier works as The Shtetl, for which he first became famous as a novelist. Complementing these works are reviews, playbills, programs, photographs of productions of his plays, and a small but revealing body of correspondence as well as several essays and appeals on behalf of European Jewry, all of which provide insight into Asch's character and his role as a spokesman for and activist in the Jewish community, both in the United States and in Europe.
Series I, Writings, occupies 13 boxes and has been organized into four subseries: Novels, Plays, Essays and Appeals, and Other Writings. Almost all of the manuscripts are holographs and typescripts in Yiddish. Within each subseries works have been arranged alphabetically by transliterated title. The English translation of the title is also noted.
The Novels include Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene), Baym Opgrunt (The War Goes On), Der Sheliekh (The Apostle), Dray Shtet (Three Cities), Toyt Urteyl (Death Sentence), Farn Mabl (Before the Flood), Gots Gefangene (Prisoners of God), and Vos Ikh Gloyb (What I Believe). The novels are written mostly in Asch's hand, although there are several major sections that seem to be in another hand. This occurs in Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene) and "Varshe" (Warsaw) in Dray Shtet (Three Cities), and has been noted in the register. There are some typescripts as well, with corrections in Asch's hand. The novels are generally complete, though there are often irregularities with pagination, including large gaps between page numbers, indicating possible missing pages. There are revisions of chapters and excised fragments, and several folders of unidentified fragments. There are also photographs and printed material in this subseries, most of them advertisements and reviews. There are also four essays on the subject of Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene), a scrapbook of reviews for Dray Shtet (folder 259), and a mounted photograph of a woodcarving inspired by Der Man fun Notseres by Abraham L. Wolbarst (folder 64). These materials have been placed after the manuscripts they pertain to, in chronological order.
The Plays, mostly holographs and typescripts written in Yiddish, include Got fun Nekome (God of Vengeance) with an English translation, Koyln (Coals), Yoysef (Josef), and Rebe Doktor Zilber (Rabbi Dr. Silber). Only the first three of these plays are complete. There are four unidentified plays, which may not be complete. There are also photographs and printed material, primarily playbills, programs and reviews. These materials have been placed after the manuscripts they pertain to, in chronological order.
Essays and Appeals contains several political essays and appeals written before World War II. Many are addressed to government officials and writers in Europe on behalf of European Jews, and Polish Jews in particular. Approximately half of the material in this section consists of holographs in Yiddish, the rest are English typescripts.
The final subseries, Other Writings, contains a brief autobiography and writings by Asch about his collection of Judaica, two short stories, one of which is unidentified and incomplete, verses in memory of H. D. Nomberg, and unidentified writing fragments. There are also playbills, programs, and reviews related to miscellaneous writings.
Series II, Correspondence, is a selection of letters to Asch from many prominent Jewish writers and organizations, revealing his wide contacts and activities in both America and Europe. In the introduction to the published catalogue, Asch mentions particularly the series of letters from Stefan Zweig, written during Hitler's ascent to power (folder 176). There also are letters to and from librarians at Yale University Library, in particular Bernhard Knollenberg, Acting Librarian James T. Babb and Curator Leon Nemoy, regarding the Asch-Rabinowitz Collection (folders 173-174). Other correspondence between Asch and these three, and chiefly concerning the acquisition of the Asch-Rabinowitz Collection, can be found in the files of the University Librarian in the Manuscripts and Archives Department at Sterling Memorial Library. The series also contains a large amount of correspondence with PEN (Poets, Essayists and Novelists) clubs throughout Europe, numerous invitations and honors from literary organizations, as well as telegrams from friends, colleagues, and business acquaintances congratulating Asch on his fiftieth birthday (folders 177-179).
Series III, Photographs, is arranged by subject and includes both studio portraits and snapshots of Asch, his family and friends. There are also photographs of Jewish art objects in Europe, and two folders of views of Palestine.
The last series, Other Papers, is arranged into Clippings, Postcards, Artwork, and Miscellaneous. The Clippings include articles, interviews, portraits of Asch and his friends; press coverage of his 50th and 60th birthday. The Postcards are mostly of Jewish antiquities in Europe and Jerusalem. The Artwork consists of a bust of Asch and sketches of Asch by Hermann Struck. The Miscellaneous section contains programs and other printed material and a corsage possibly once worn by Mrs. Asch.
Oversize contains two types of material. The first consists of selected oversize pages from various manuscripts, for which reduced or sectioned reference copies have been retained with the rest of the manuscript for purposes of continuity. The other type of material consists of items which have not been replaced by reference copies, including two major parts from Der Sheliekh (The Apostle) and Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene).
Man fun Natseres. Yiddish. 1939; American literature -- Jewish authors; Authors, Yiddish -- United States -- Archives; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) -- United States -- Archives; Photographic prints; Asch, Sholem, 1880-1957 -- Archives; Babb, James E. (James Elisha), 1864-1934; Knollenberg, Bernhard, 1892-1973; Lipsi, Morice, 1898-; Nemoy, Leon, 1901-; Zweig, Stefan, 1881-1942; PEN (Organization)
- Writings, 1922-1943; Series I; 4.15; (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Writings are arranged by type, and then alphabetically
  by transliterated title, with the English translation in
  parentheses. Manuscripts of novels have been divided by
  chapters or at logical breaking points. Oversize pages
  have been replaced with photocopies and placed in the Oversize series. Where multiple hands appear in a
  manuscript, this has been noted.
  - NOVELS
    - Baym Opgrunt (The War Goes On)
      - Volume I, chapters 1-15, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - Volume I, chapters 16-end, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      - Volume II, chapters 1-17, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      - Volume II, chapters 18-end, holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Advertisements, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Stored also in: Oversize, Box 18,
        folder 243
      - Reviews, 1936-37 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        folder 244
    - Dray Shtet (Three Cities)
      - "Peterburg" (Petersburg), part I (incomplete), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - "Peterburg" (Petersburg), part II, chapters 1-7, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - "Peterburg" (Petersburg), part II, chapters 8-end, holograph, corrected (Box 2, Folder 15)
        Includes two revisions of chapter
        14
      - "Varshe" (Warsaw), part II, chapters 1-6, holograph, corrected with additions in another hand (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
      - "Varshe" (Warsaw), part II, chapters 7-end, holograph, corrected (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
      - "Varshe" (Warsaw), part II, chapters 1-17, holograph, corrected with additions in another hand (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
      - "Moskve" (Moscow), part I, chapters 1-13, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 24-27)
      - "Moskve" (Moscow), part I, chapters 14-end, holograph, corrected (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - "Moskve" (Moscow), part II, chapters 1-11, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
      - "Moskve" (Moscow), part II, chapters 12-20, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Review--"A Tale of Three Cities," by Padraic Colum, typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Advertisements, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 35)
        folder 245
      - Reviews, 1930-37 (Box 3, Folder 36)
        folder 246
      - Reviews of Petersburg, 1929-30 (Box 3, Folder 37)
        folder 247
      - Scrapbook of reviews, 1933
    - Farn Mabl (Before the Flood)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Dray Shtet (Three Cities), Box 3, folder 37
    - Gots Gefangene (Prisoners of God)
      - Chapters 1-4, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Chapters 5-9, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Chapters 10-20, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
      - Reviews, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 42)
        Stored also in: Oversize, Box 18, folder 248
    - Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene)
      - First revision, part I, chapters 1-8, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 43-45)
      - First revision, part I, chapters 12-[end?], holograph, corrected (Box 5, Folder 46-47)
      - First revision, end of part I?, beginning with "The Sermon on the Mount," holograph, corrected (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Second revision, part I, chapters 3-end of part I, holograph, corrected, partially written in another hand (Box 5, Folder 49-50)
      - Third revision, part II, chapters 12-18, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 5, Folder 51)
      - Part II, chapters 1-[end?], holograph and typescript, corrected, with additions in another hand (Box 5, Folder 52-55)
      - Part II, chapters 2-10, holograph, corrected, partially written in another hand (Box 6, Folder 56-57)
      - Part III, holograph, corrected, n.d.
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 58)
      - Related Writings
        - "Mayn Entfer" (My Reply). Two incomplete versions, typescripts, carbon copies, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 59)
        - "A Vort tsu di Lezer" (A Word to the Readers), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 60)
        - "Di Shuldige" (The Guilty Ones), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 61)
        - "Sholem Asch's Picture of Jesus. An Address to the Chicago Ethical Society", 1939 Nov 19 (Box 6, Folder 62)
      - Book jackets, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 62a)
      - Reviews, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 63)
        folder 249
      - Mounted photograph of wood carving by Abraham L. Wolbarst, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Mottke The Thief
      - Advertisements, [1933-35] (Box 6, Folder 65)
        folder 250
      - Reviews, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 66)
        folder 251
    - Der Sheliekh (The Apostle)
      - Part I, holograph, corrected, n.d.
      - Part II, chapters 1-11, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 67-70)
      - Part II, chapters 12-22, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 71-72)
      - Part II, chapters 23-30, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 73-75)
      - Part II, chapters 31-35, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 76)
      - Part III, chapters 1-12, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 77-78)
      - Part III, chapters 13-end, holograph, corrected (Box 8, Folder 79-80)
      - Excised fragments, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 81)
      - Unidentified pieces, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 82)
      - Advertisements, 1943
      - Reviews, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 83)
        Stored also in: Oversize, Box 22,
        folder 253
    - Der Tehilim Yid (Salvation)
      - Holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 8, Folder 84)
      - Advertisements, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 85)
        folder 254
      - Reviews, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 86)
        folder 255
    - Toyt Urteyl (Death Sentence)
      - Holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 87-88)
        Title also translated as Judge Not
    - Uncle Moses
      - Playbill, 1934 Apr 30 (Box 9, Folder 89)
      - Photograph for novel, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - Vos Ikh Gloyb (What I Believe)
      - Chapters 1-10, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 9, Folder 91-93)
      - Chapters 11-end, holograph, corrected (Box 9, Folder 94-96)
  - PLAYS
    - Children of Abraham
      - Reviews, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 97)
        folder 256
    - Got fun Nekome (God of Vengeance)
      - Holograph, corrected, bound (Box 9, Folder 98)
      - Translation by Isaac Goldberg, typescript, annotated, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 99)
      - Advertisements, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 100)
      - Programs, 1922-23, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 101)
      - Copies of letters to Harry Weinberger, producer, 1923 Apr (Box 9, Folder 102)
      - Playbill for Apollo production, [1923]
      - "The God of Vengeance" Is the Play Immoral? - Is it a Great Drama? Bound pamphlet, [1923] (Box 9, Folder 103)
      - Newspaper reviews, [1923], n.d. (Box 9, Folder 104)
      - Photographs of the performance in Sweden, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 105)
        Actors: Agnes Mowinkel, Holst
        Jensen, Signe Tharaldsen, Mette
        Bull
      - Playbills, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 106)
        folder 257
    - Kidush Hashem ( Supreme Sacrifice )
      - Reviews, 1933, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 107)
      - Programs, 1934, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Koyln (Coal)
      - Holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 109-110)
    - Yoysef (Joseph)
      - Typescript, corrected. Lacks leaves 5-17; text partly supplied in "Naye Folkstsaytung", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 111)
        Stored also in: Oversize, Bsd,
        folder 283
    - Fragments
      - Rebe Doktor Zilber (Rabbi Dr. Silber) Leaf 70 only, typescript, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - Unidentified plays
      - Play #1. Characters: Anton, Greek, The mute, Slosha, Khaskel, Tane, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 113)
      - Play #2. Setting: "A hot, hot evening-- the dwellers of a house in Essex Street on the East side of New York come outside to sleep in the court...." Principal character: Shloyme Volf, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 114-115)
      - Play #3. Characters: Master John Tomkins, nine years old; Mr. Davis, Governess; First director of Tomkinsville; Technical director of Tomkinsville; newspaper people, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 116)
      - Play #4. Second act, two scenes, entitled "A Greek," and "The dream of [?]" Characters: Zeytser, Zaslusha, The Greek, The Chineseman (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - ESSAYS AND APPEALS
    - Address at the Congress of PEN clubs in Ragusa, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - Appeal to PEN clubs to lend support to protests against persecution of Jews in Germany, typescript (Box 12, Folder 119)
    - Appeal to Poles to do justice to their Jewish fellow citizens, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - "A Briv tsu di Panes fun Poyln" (A Letter to the Gentlemen of Poland), holograph, corrected (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Defense of his stand against a meeting to protest against anti-Jewish riots at Lvov, holograph, corrected (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Draft of letter to the President of the Jewish PEN club in Warsaw, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - "Feliks Varburg iz Nito Meyr" (Felix Warburg is No More), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 124)
      Includes carbon copy of typescript
      English translation (incomplete).
    - "Der Geler Flek" (The Yellow Badge), typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - "Khizoyen Eyropa" (Vision of Europe), typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - "Lozen Mir Oysshrayen Unzer Veytig" (Let Us Give Voice to Our Pain), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - On the Persecution of Jews in Poland, holograph, corrected (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Papers relating to the Joint Distribution Committee
      - "The Mourner at the Marriage Fete," typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 129)
      - "The Political and Economic Position of the Jews in Poland," typescript (Box 12, Folder 130)
      - "Situation of the Jews in Central Europe," typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 131)
      - "What is to be Done?" typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 132)
      - "A Word to the Poles," typescript, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 133)
      - Miscellaneous letters and addresses, 1935-42, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 134)
    - Prayer for strength in adversity, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 135)
    - Radio address over the Palestine network, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 12, Folder 136)
    - "Tsu di Daytshe Shriftshteler" (Against Persecution of Jews in Germany), typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 137)
      Includes German translation,
      "Offener Brief an die deutschen
      Schriftsteller," typescript,
      corrected
    - "A Vort Vegn Mayn Zamlung fun Yidishe Sforim" (A Word About My Collection), typescript corrected, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - Autobiography, typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Fragments of unidentified short story (hero named Rabinowitz), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - "In the Valley of Death," The New York Times Magazine, 1943 Feb 7
    - "Mishpet Nisht o Ir Rikhter" (Judge Not), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 141)
      Verses in memory of H.D. Nomberg
    - Playbills, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 142)
    - Programs, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 143)
    - "Reshimos Sforim" (List of Books) typescript, annotated, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - Reviews, 1929-43 (Box 13, Folder 145-146)
      folder 258
    - "Shoen Gekredentst dem Tish" (A Nicely Set Table), holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 147)
    - Speech in PEN News, 1934 Feb (Box 13, Folder 148)
    - Fragments, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 149)
- Correspondence, 1923-1956; Series II; 0.4; (1 box)
  Correspondence consists mostly of letters written to
  Asch, with a few third party letters noted. The few
  letters from Asch, also, are noted. Each correspondent
  is listed below, except in the case of the educational
  and cultural organizations file, which stands as
  originally cataloged in the Judaica Collection.
  - "A" general, 1931-40, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 150)
    Contains:
    Alperin, A.
    American Pro-Falasha Committee, Inc.
    Aron, Willy
    Asch, Matilda
    From Sholem Asch, with postscript
    by Siegfried Schmitz
    Association Culturelle Israélite
  - Arlosoroff Foundation, 1933 (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - "B" general, 1930-40, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 152)
    Balch, Earle H.
    Barr, Norman Burton
    Bloch, Jean Richard
    Bradley, Preston
    Brod, Max
    Bronstein, M. [?]
    Brunot, Ferdinand
  - Babb, James T.
    See: Yale University Library, Box 14, folder 173
  - Bialik, Hayyim Nahman, 1927-30 (Box 14, Folder 153)
  - "C" general, 1926-39, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 154)
    Cahan, Abraham
    Cantor, Hyman
    Central Yiddish Culture Organization
    Chagall, Marc
    Chanin, N.
    Chapiro, Joseph
    Charney, Samuel
    Collinson, C. S.
    Colum, Mary Maguire